Juan Pablo Rabino Python Developer / Team Leader



Personal Summary

Fast-paced and objective oriented software developer and team leader. I have grown professionally from working in electronics and telecommunications to full time software developer and team leader. I have now over 12 years (+3 as lead) of experience working in several projects covering a broad set of technologies from laboratory automation and IoT, to back-end services for finance and banking applications.

I am in the lookout for my next opportunity to grow as a leader and team builder reference in the field.

Soft Skills

- Management and Leadership.
- Client-facing relationships.
- Product Owner.
- Communication.
- Agile Practices.
- Mentorship.

Education

 Electronics Engineer, Universidad de Buenos Aires.

Technical Skills

- · Core Python.
- Testing.
- OpenCV.
- Pandas/Numpy/Scipy
- Rest API.
- Reactls / React-native.
- IoT and Telecoms.
 - RF/Satellite comms
 - Wireless protocols
- Django/Flask.

Professional Experience

JP Morgan Chase.
Buenos Aires, Argentina
Feb 2020 - Present
Python Software Engineering lead, Vice-President.

As VP I'm in charge of a *team of 17 developers* across 3 different projects in parallel. Our goal is to provide unified, opinionated solutions to a broad group of internal customers; consolidating implementations, modernizing the technology stack, reducing operational costs and improving time to market. We work on full stack, event driven architectures to provide low-latency, high volume and high availability data applications, such as blotters, tickets, risk calculation tools, reporting, etc.

Apart from that I volunteer for philanthropic initiatives to teach and mentor youngsters of low-income households to get their first job in technology.

Roble Lab, Buenos Aires, Argentina, Jan 2021 - Present.

Software architect.

Roble is a side-project company that develops IoT solutions on several fields, from video feed based sensors to air quality measurements.

My role is to design and implement the full back-end architecture that supports the network infrastructure which is AWS cloud-based. For this, I rely on every piece of Python technology and library I can get my hands on. This keeps me up to date and being creative with the latest on the field.

JP Morgan Chase. Buenos Aires, Argentina July 2018 - Feb 2020 Python Senior Developer

Building up on my previous experience, I got hired by JPM directly.

Over the course of 2019, I built a team from scratch up to 15 developers from a wide range of seniorities to cover the Trade Management space of the platform.

This requires heavy analytic skills, deep understanding of software architecture models and a fast troubleshooting and resolution mindset.

We created several tools to reduce the "time to recover" for most of our applications while we on-boarded new financial products and desks to the platform.

Globant, Buenos Aires, Argentina Apr 2017 - July 2018 Python Semi Senior Developer

Joined as Python developer for Globant's Digital Content Studio.

I was assigned as "ranger" at client's premises working as developer at JP Morgan for their core Athena program.

I specialized in data analysis and representation for financial applications, such as risk, PnL analysis, etc. I also worked on a Python training program for the new joiners to the team from other technologies/departments.

National Commission for Space Activities (CONAE), Buenos Aires, Argentina Dec. 2013 - Apr. 2017 Flight Segment Engineer, SAOCOM Project

The SAOCOM project consists of 2 satellites that will, in short, observe and measure the levels of humidity of the planet at surface level.

I was part of the EMC team that is in charge of all the validation and verifications that assures the reliability of all the components.

Also, I am part of the Ground Segment and SAOCOM System, in charge of the whole functional test, analysis and verification of the mission.

My main tasks include:

- Laboratory setup and configuration of high precision RF devices.
- Test procedures coordination, documentation and analysis.
- Development of software interfaces for test automation on all equipment in order to properly control the measuring and test environment.
- Software development for image processing and data analysis.

Previous Experience

Responsables Inscriptos SRL. Crespo, Entre Ríos, Argentina Sept. 2010 - Dec, 2013 R&D engineer

RI SRL was focused on delivering solutions to reduce energy consumption in cycling charges. This was achieved through the design and implementation of wireless, low-consumption networks.

My tasks as R&D Engineer research and development for new tech solutions for the company. Mainly, I focused on ZigBee embedded systems for communication, control and monitoring.

Besides, I was responsible for the software design and development. I designed, tested, documented and distributed all the user interfaces (GUI) for all the company products.

Emerging Markets Communications Corp.

Redditch,UK Dec. 2009 - Feb 2010 Teleport Engineer

As teleport satellite Engineer, I was in charge of maintenance and resources assignation for the company's teleport in Redditch. UK.

My main tasks were to improve the reliability to ensure SLA levels for the links. My focus was on resolving all the issues in terms of possible escalation of the teleport. I have also documented the routine tasks for the teleport to pass along to future Engineers.

Emerging Markets Communications Corp. Buenos Aires, Argentina Dec, 2007 - Sept. 2010 NOC Engineer.

As NOC operator, my main task was to proactively monitor and quickly diagnose all network links in order to keep high standard SLA's. Within less than a year as NOC operator, I extensively improved my satellite network knowledge and my proficiency in IP service such as VoIP and Real time Video Conference. I had the opportunity to work for high profile costumers (such as UN programs, IMF, World Bank, CitiBank, HSBC, etc) always under really compromising death lines. This way I learned to work under pressure, always focused on the trouble resolution and improvement of customer experiences.

As 2nd tier NOC Engineer my focus was to proactively deliver solutions in order to guarantee the reliability of the customer's satellite links. These tasks included the constant improvement of RMA processes and training of Field Engineers to properly troubleshoot and document for future references. I addressed directly to major costumer's HQ, such as:

- UN WFP (United Nations World Food Program)
- UNHCR (United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees)
- UNDP (United Nations Development Program)
- UNICEF (United Nations Children's Fund)

Apart from this, my tasks included the constant training for 1st tier operators as I was their first escalation point. I developed process solutions to improve the NOC's daily tasks. Also, my KRA's included the analysis and resolution of RF network problems such as degradation, interference, chain balancing, etc.

Education

2004-2010

Universidad de Buenos Aires, Facultad de Ingenieria

Electronics Engineer.

- Final Course Project: Design and implementation for house alarm systems, through ZigBee communication.

Other Courses and certifications

2022	Amazon Web Services	Certified Cloud Practitioner
2012	Universidad Tecnologica Nacional	Python Developer. Advanced
2012	Universidad Tecnologica Nacional	Android Developer
2008	Emerging Markets Communications	Teleport Maintenance and VSAT deployment.
2008	Emerging Markets Communications	CCNA Training for routing and switching configuration on Cisco Devices.